SICP Lectures-2a Subtitles
(http://www.archive.org/download/halmit2a/Lecture-2a.mpg)
Copyright (C)  2010  Toni Moll.
Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3
or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
Free Documentation License".
Well, yesterday was easy.
You learned all of
the rules of programming in lisp,
Almost all of them,
And so at this point
you're now certified programmers
you could say.
However,
I suppose what we did is, ...
... we sort of got you
a little bit of into an easy state.
Do you still believe
it's possible, you know, ...
that this might be
programming in basic or pascal
with just a funny syntax.
Today, that illusion ...
... or, you can
no longer support that belief.
What we're going to do today
is to completely smash that.
So, let's start out, ...
... ah, by writing a few programs
on the blackboard that have a
lot in common with each other.
What we're gonna do,
is try
to make some abstractions ...
... that are not ones
that are easy to make
in most languages.
To start with some simple ones
that you can make
in most languages ...
Supposing I want to write
the mathematical expression
which adds up a bunch of integers.
So if I want to write down,
lets say, the sum
from i=a to b of i.
Now you know that's an easy thing
to compute a closed form for, ...
... and I'm not interested in that,
but I'm gonna write a program
that adds up those integers.
That's rather easy to do.
To say,
define the sum of the integers
from a to b ...
... to be, well,
it's the following two possibilities:
If a is greater than b,
then there's nothing to be done,
and the answer is zero.
This is how you're going to
have to think recursively.
If I have an easy case
that I know the answer to,
just write it down.
Otherwise I'm going to try
to reduce this problem
to a simpler problem, ...
... and maybe in this case
I'm gonna make a subproblem
with a simpler problem and then
do something to the result.
So the easiest way to do this:
You say that
I'm going to add the index,
which in this case is a, ...
... to the result of
adding up
the integers from a+1 to b.
Now at this point,
you should have no trouble
looking at such a definition.
Indeed, coming
up with such a thing might
be a little hard in synthesis, ...
... but being able to read it,
at this point, should be easy.
What it says to you is:
Well, here is the
subproblem I'm going to solve:
I'm going to try
to add up the integers, ...
... one fewer integer than
I added up
for the whole problem, ...
I'm adding up one fewer one ...
... and that's the problem,
once I've solved it,
i'm gonna add a to that ...
... and that will be
the answer to this problem.
And in the simplest case
I don't have to do any work.
Now I'm also going to write down
another simple one just like this,
which is the
mathematical expression of
sum of the squares
from i=a to b.
And again a very simple program.
And
indeed it starts the same way.
If a is greater than b,
then the answer is zero.
And of course we're
beginning to see ...
... that
there's something wrong with me
writing this down again.
Okay, it's the same program.
It's the sum of the square of a ...
... and the sum of the squares of
the increment and b.
Now if you
look at these things, these
programs are almost identical.
Okay, there's not much to
distinguish them.
They have the same
first clause in the conditional, ...
... and the same predicate
and the same consequent, ...
... and the alternatives
are very similar too.
They only differ by the fact that,
whereas here I have A,
here I have the square of A.
The only other difference, but
this one is sort of unessential, ...
... is that
the name of this procedure
is SUM-INT, ...
... whereas
the name of this procedure
is SUM-SQUARE.
so the things that vary
between these two are very small.
Now, whenever you see yourself
writing the same thing down
more than once ...
... there is something wrong,
and you shouldn't be doing it.
And the reason is not because
it's a waste of time
to write something down
more than once.
It's because there's some idea
here, a very simple idea, ...
... which has to do with
the sigma notation.
Right, it's this much
not depending upon
what it is I'm adding up.
And I would like to be able to
have always, whenever trying
to make complicated systems
and to understand them ...
... it's crucial to divide the things
up and do as many pieces
as I can, ...
... each of which
I understand separately.
I would like to understand
the way of adding things up ...
... independently of
what it is I'm adding up.
So that I can use that,
having debugged it once.
Having understood it once.
And having been able to share
that,
among many different uses of it.
Here we have another example.
This is Leibnitz's formula
for finding pi over 8.
Let's say,
a funny ugly mess it's what it is.
Something like,
1/(1*3)+
1/(5*7)+
1/(9*11)+
... .
And for some reason,
things like this tend to ...
... tend to have
interesting values like pi/8.
But, what do we see here?
It's the same program,
or almost the same program.
It's a sum.
Okay, so,
we're seeing the sigma notation,
although over here, we're dealing
with incrementing by 4, ...
... that's a
slightly different problem, ...
... which means that over here
I have to change a by 4,
as you see right over here.
It's not by one.
The other thing of course, ...
... is that the thing that is
represented by square ...
... in the previous sum of squares, ...
... or A when
I'm adding up the integers, ...
... well,
here I have a different thing
I'm adding up, a different term ...
which is 1 over a, 1 over a,
1 over a times a plus two.
But the rest of this program
is identical.
Well, anytime we have
a bunch of things like this
that are identical, ...
... we're gonna have to come up
with some sort of abstraction
to cover them.
If you think about this
what you've learned so far ...
... is the rules of some language:
some primitives,
some means of combination,
almost all of them, ...
... the means of abstraction,
... but what you haven't learned is
common patterns of usage.
Now most of the time you learn
idioms when learning a language.
There's a common pattern,
that means things,
that are useful to know,
like a flash.
And if you build up
a great number of them ...
If you're a fortran programmer,
of course
everybody knows how to ...
ah, what do you do ...?
... for example, to get an integer
which is
the biggest integer in something.
Okay, it's a classic thing.
Every fortran programmer knows
how to do that.
And if you don't know that
you're a real hard worker,
'cause it takes a long time
to think it out.
However,
one of the things you can do
in this language
that we're showing you, ...
... is not only that you're knowing
something like that, ...
... but you give
the knowledge of that
a name.
And it's so that's what
we're gonna be going after
right now.
Okay, well let's see what
these things have in common.
Okay, right over here, ...
... we have
what appears to be
a general pattern, ...
... a general pattern
which covers all of the cases
we've seen so far.
There is, ...
some procedure
which is being defined, ...
... it has two arguments,
which are a lower bound
and an upper bound.
The lower bound is tested to be
greater than the upper bound, ...
... and if it is greater,
then the result is zero.
Otherwise we're going to
do something to the lower bound,
which is the index
of the computation, ...
... and add that result
to the result of calling the
procedure recursively on ...
... the lower bound incremented
by some next operation, ...
... with the same upper bound as I had before.
So this is a general pattern.
And what I'd like to do, is be able
to name this general pattern a bit.
Well that's sort of easy, ...
... because one of the
things I'm going to do right now, ...
... is ...
there's nothing special
about numbers.
Numbers are just one kind of data.
And it seems to me
perfectly reasonable to give
all sorts of names to
all kinds of data, ...
... for example procedures.
And many languages allow you
to have procedural arguments.
And right now we're gonna
talk about procedural arguments.
It's very easy to deal with.
And shortly we'll do some
remarkable things that are not
like procedural arguments.
So here we'll define
our sigma notation.
This is called SUM and it takes
a TERM, and A, a NEXT-er,
and B as arguments.
so it takes four arguments.
There is nothing particularly
special about me writing
this in lower case.
I hope that it doesn't
confuse you it's all
upper-case right now.
The machine doesn't care.
But these two
arguments are different -
These are not numbers, these
are gonna be procedures for
computing something
given a number.
TERM will be a procedure, which,
when given an index,
Will produce the value of
the term for that index.
NEXT will, when given
an index, produce the next index.
This will be for counting.
And it's just very simple.
It's exactly what you see.
If A is greater than B,
then the result is 0, ...
... otherwise it's the sum of
TERM applied to A ...
... and the SUM of TERM,
next index ...
(we'll write it this way)
Now I'd like you to see
some things first of all.
I was writing here, and
I ran out of space.
What I did is start indenting
according to the
pretty-printing rule ...
... which says I align all of
the arguments of the procedure,
so that I can see which
ones go together.
And this is something I do
automatically and I want you
to learn how to do that, too, ...
... so your programs can be
read and understood.
However...
what do we have here...
we have 4 arguments:
The procedure,
the lower-bound index,
the way to get the next index,
and the upper bound.
What was passed along -
on the recursive call -
is, indeed, the same procedure,
'cause I'm gonna need it again, ...
... the next index - which
is using the next procedure
to compute it, ...
... the procedure for
computing next, which I also
have, that's separately;
and that's different.
The procedure for computing
next is different from the
next index, ...
... which is the result of using
next on the last index.
And I also have to pass
along the upper bound.
So this captures most of these,
and the other nice programs
that we were playing with.
So using this, we can write down
the original programs as
instances of SUM very simply.
... of A and B ...
Well I'm gonna need an
identity procedure here,
because, ah, ...
... the sum of the integers
requires me to - in this case -
compute a term for every integer,
but the term procedure doesn't
want to do anything to
that integer.
So the identity procedure
on A is A.
... or X or whatever.
And I wanna say: the SUM of
using IDENTITY of the
term procedure, ...
... and using A as
the initial index, ...
... and the incrementer being
the way to get the next index, ...
... and B being the high bound,
the upper bound.
This procedure does exactly the
same as the
sum of the integers over here.
Computes the same answer.
Now one thing you
should see of course, ...
... is that there's nothing
very special over here, about,
what I used as a
formal parameter.
I could have for example written this X.
And it doesn't matter.
I just wanted you to see, that
this name does not conflict ...
... with this name at all -
it's an internal name.
For the second procedure here,
the sum of the squares, it's
even a little bit easier.
And what do we have to do?
Nothing more than
add up the squares.
And this is the procedure that
each index will be given... will
be given each index... - yes...
Each index will have this done
to it to get the term.
That's the thing that maps
against term over here.
Then I have A as a lower bound, ...
... the incrementor as a
next term method, ...
... and B as the upper bound.
And finally, just for the thing that
we did about pythons...
Pythons are sort of, well...
it's even easier to think about
them this way.
'cause I don't have to think!
What I'm doing is separating: the
thing I'm adding up, from the
method of doing the addition.
And so we have here,
for example:
... PI-SUM A B
of a SUM of things.
I'm gonna write the term
procedure here explicitly, without
giving it a name.
This is anonymously, I don't
necessarily have to give a
name to something.
If I just wanna use it once.
And of course I can write sort of
a expression that produces a
procedure.
I'm going to write the greek
lambda letter here, ...
... instead of L-A-M-B-D-A
in general to avoid taking up
a lot of space on blackboards.
Unfortunately we don't have
lambda keys on our keyboards,
maybe we can convince our
friends in the computer industry
that this is important.
Lambda of i...
it's the quotient of 1 and
the product of i and sum of i, 2.
Starting at A;
the way of incrementing being
that procedure of an index i,
which adds i to 4, ...
... and b being the upper bound.
So we can see that this is
notation - the invention of the
procedure that takes a procedural
argument - allows us to compress
a lot of these procedures into
one thing.
This procedure SUM covers
a whole bunch of ideas.
Now just why is this important?
I tried to say before that it helps
us divide a problem into
two pieces.
And indeed it does.
For example, if someone came up
with a different way of
implementing this, ...
... which of course, one might.
Here is for example, an
iterative implementation of SUM.
Iterative implementations for
some reasons might be better ...
... than the
recursive implementation.
But the important thing is
it's different.
Now, supposing I had written my
programs this way,
that you see ...
... on the blackboard on the left.
... It's correct. The left.
Well then, if I want to change the
method of addition, ...
... then I'd have to change
each of these.
Whereas, if I write them like
this, that you see here, ...
... then the method by which I
did the addition is encapsulated
in the procedure SUM.
That decomposition allows me
to independently change one
part of the program, ...
... and improve it perhaps, ...
... without changing the other
part, that was written for
some other cases.
Thank you, are there
any questions?
- Yes Sir.
- [muffled] ... NEXT A ... [muffled]
- Yes, it's the same problem.
I'm sure you're gonna ...
you're gonna
have to work on this, ...
... this is hard, the first time
you've ever seen something
like this.
What I have here, is: Procedures
can be named by variables.
Procedures are not special.
Actually, SUM-SQuare is a
variable, which has gotten a
value, which is a procedure.
This is DEFINEd SUM-SQuare to
be lambda of A and B something.
So the procedures can be
named, therefore they can be ...
... passed from one procedure to
another, as arguments.
What we're doing here is we're
passing the procedure TERM
as an argument to SUM.
Just so that we get it around
in the next recursion.
Here we're passing the procedure
NEXT as an argument also.
However, here we're _using_ the
procedure NEXT - that's what the
parentheses mean.
We're applying NEXT to A to get
the next value of A.
If you look at what NEXT is
mapped against we see ...
Remember, that the way you
think about this is that
you substitute the argument
with the former parameters,
in the body.
If you're ever confused, think of
it that way.
Well, over here is the
sum of the integers.
I substitute identity for
term and 1+, the incrementor, for
NEXT in the body.
Well, the identity procedure on
A is what I get here.
The identity is being
passed along.
And here I have increment, 1+,
being applied to A.
And 1+ is being passed along.
Does that clarify the situation?
- We could also define quickly
those two functions and then
pass them...
- Oh yeah, sure. What we could
do is, we could have
given names to them.
Just like I did here. It's like I
gave you various ways,
so you could see it, a variety.
I mean, here, I defined a thing,
which I passed the name of,
I referenced it by its name.
But the thing was in fact: that
procedure of one argument X,
which is X.
The identity procedure is just
lambda of X, X. Right?
And that's what you're
seeing here.
Here I happend to just write its
canonical name, there for you
to see.
Okay?
So should we take our
5-minute break?
As I said, ...
... computers to make
people happy,
not people to make
computers happy.
And, for the most part, the
reason why we introduced all
this abstraction stuff, is to
make it so that ...
... programs can be more easily
written and more easily read.
Let's try to understand what's the
most complicated program we've
seen so far,
using a little bit of
this abstraction stuff.
We can look at the slide.
This is the Heron of Alexandria's
method of computing square
roots, that we saw yesterday.
And, let's see...
Well, in any case, this program's
a little complicated.
And at the current state of your
thinking, you just can't look at
that and say,
"Oh this obviously means
something very, very clear."
It's not obvious from looking at
the program what it's computing.
There is some loop here
inside try, ...
... and the loop does something
about trying the
improvement of y, ...
... there's something called
improve, which does some
averaging, and quotienting,
and things like that.
But what's the real idea?
Can we make it clear
what the idea is?
Well, I think we can.
I think we can use abstraction,
that we have learned about
so far,
to clarify what's going on.
Now what we have,
mathematically, is ...
... a procedure for improving a
guess for square roots.
And if y is a guess for a square
root, then what we want to
get, we'll call a function f -
this is for the
means of improvement.
I wanna get y plus x over y,
over 2 - it's the average of
y and x divided by y - as ...
... the improved value for the
square root of x.
Such that, one thing you can
notice about this function f,
is that, f of the square root of x,
is in fact the square root of x.
Whereas if I take the
square root of x as
substitute for y here, ...
... I see the square root of x, plus
x divided by the square root of x,
- which is the square root of x -
... that's two times the
square root of x divided by 2
is the square root of x.
So in fact, what we're really
looking for, is ...
... we're looking for a fixed point.
A fixed-point of the function f.
A fixed point is the place which
has the property, that if you
put it into the function, you get
the same value out.
Now I suppose if we were giving
some nice boring lecture and you
have in front of you a HP35 desk
calculator, like I used to have,
when I went to boring lectures, ...
... and you think it is really
boring, you put it into
radiance mode, ...
... and hit cosine,
and hit cosine,
and hit cosine.
And eventually you end up
with .734 or something like that.
.743, I don't remember
what exactly.
It gets closer and closer to that.
Some functions have the property
that you can find their fixed point
by iterating the function.
And that's essentially what's
happening in the square root
program by Heron's method.
So let's see if we can write that
down, that idea.
Now I'm not gonna say how I can
compute fixed points yet.
There might be more than
one way.
But the first thing to do, ...
... is to say what I just said.
I'm gonna say it specifically,
for square root.
The square root of x is the
fixed point ...
... of that procedure, ...
... which takes an argument y and
averages x divided by y with y.
And it starts up with an initial
guess, for the fixed point, of 1.
Doesn't matter where it starts.
A theorem of having to do with
square roots.
So what you're seeing here, is
I'm just trying to write out, by
wishful thinking ...
I don't know how I'm gonna
make fixed point happen.
We'll worry about that later.
But if somehow I had a way of
finding the fixed point of the
function computed by
this procedure,
then I would have...
That would be the square root
that I'm looking for.
Okay, now let's see how
we're gonna write ...
How we're gonna come up with
fixed points.
Well, it's very simple actually.
I'm gonna write an abbreviated
version here, just so we
understand it.
I'm gonna find the
fixed point of a function f.
Actually...
The fixed point of the function,
computed by the procedure,
whose name will be f in
this procedure.
How's that? Long sense.
Starting with a particular
starting value.
Well I'm going to have a
little loop inside here, ...
which is going to push the
button on the calculator,
repeatedly,
hoping that it'll eventually
converge.
And we will say here.
Internal loops are written by
defining internal procedures.
Well, one thing I'm gonna have to
do is, I'm going to have to say
wether I'm done.
And the way to decide when I'm
done is when the old value and
the new value are close enough, so
I can't distinguish them anymore.
It's the saner thing you do on the
calculator, unless you look for
more precision and eventually
you run out of precision.
So, the old value and the
new value
And I'm going to say here:
if I can't distinguish them,
if they're close enough, ...
... - and we'll have to worry about
what that is soon - ...
... the OLD value and NEW value
are CLOSE-ENOUGH to each other,
then let's pick the NEW value
as the answer,
... otherwise I'm gonna iterate
around again,
with the next value of OLD
being the current value of NEW,
and the next value of NEW being
the result of calling F on NEW.
And so this is my iteration
loop that pushes the button
on the calculator.
I'd basically think of it as
having two registers in the
calculator, OLD and NEW.
And at each step,
NEW becomes OLD, and
NEW gets F of NEW.
So this is the thing where I'm
getting the next value.
And now I'm gonna
start this thing up, ...
... by giving two values.
Now I wrote that on the
black board to be slow,
so you could see this.
This is the first time you've seen
something quite this complicated,
I think.
However, we might wanna see
the whole thing over here...
In this transparency,
or slide, or whatever.
What we have, is all of the
details that are required to
make this thing work.
I have a way of getting a
tolerance for a close-enough
procedure, which we see here.
The close-enough procedure, it
tests wether u and v are close
enough, by seeing if the absolute
value of the difference in u and v
is less than the given tolerance.
And here is the iteration
loop that I just wrote on the
blackboard,
and the
initialization for it, which is right there.
It's very simple.
But let's see, I haven't told
you enough.
It's actually easier than this.
There is more structure to this
problem than I've already
told you.
Like, why should this work?
Why should it converge?
Well, here's a hairy theorem of
mathematics tied up in what I've
written here.
Why is it that I should assume
that by iterating, averaging the
quotient of x and y, and y,
that I should get the right answer?
It isn't so obvious.
Surely there are other things,
other procedures, which compute
functions, whose fixed points
would also be the square root.
For example, the obvious one.
The obvious one will be a new
function g which maps y to
x over y.
That's even simpler.
The fixed point of g is surely
the square root also.
And it's a simpler procedure.
Why am I not using it.
Well I suppose we know.
Supposing x is 2, and I start out
with 1,
Then
if I divide one into two, I get two,
and then if
I divide two into two, I get one.
If I divide one into two I get two,
and two into two I get one,
and I never get
any closer to the square root.
This oscillates.
So what we have is a
signal processing system.
An electrical circuit
which is oscillating,
and I wanna damp out
these oscillations.
Well I can do that.
See what I'm really doing here,
when I'm taking my average,
the average is averaging the
last two values of something
which oscillates,
getting something in between.
A classic way of damping out
oscillations in a signal
processing system.
So why don't we write down the
strategy I just said in a more
clear way?
Well that's easy enough.
I'm gonna define the square root
of X to be a fixed point of the
procedure resulting from
average damping.
So we have a procedure
resulting from
AVERAGE-DAMP ...
... of the procedure ..
that procedure of y, which ...
divides x by y, starting out at 1.
But AVERAGE-DAMP is a special
procedure, that's going to take
a procedure as its argument,
and return a procedure
as its value.
Its a generalization, that says:
Given a procedure, it's the thing
which produces a procedure which
averages the last the last value .. -
the value before and after
running the procedure.
You can use it for anything if you
wanna damp out oscillations.
So let's write that down.
It's very easy.
And stylistically here I'm gonna
use lambda notation, 'cause it's
much easier to think when you're
dealing with procedures that
manipulate procedures to
understand that the procedures
are the objects I'm dealing with,
so I'm gonna use lambda notation
here - not always, I don't
always use it,
but very specifically here,
to expand on that idea, to
elucidate it.
Well, AVERAGE-DAMP is a
procedure, which takes a
procedure as its argument,
which we'll call f.
And what does it produce?
It produces as its value - the body
of this procedure is a thing
which produces a procedure, the
constructor for procedures
right here,
of one argument x, which
averages f of x with x.
This is a very special thing.
I think for the first time
you're seeing a procedure which
produces a procedure as its value.
And this procedure takes a
procedure f, and does something
to it, to produce a new procedure
of one argument x,
which averages
f, this f, applied to x,
and x itself.
Using the context here, I apply
average damping to the procedure
which is just divides x by y,
it's a division.
And then finding the fixed point
of that and that's a clearer way of
writing down what I wrote
down over here:
Wherever it was... here.
'cause it tells why I'm writing this
down.
I suppose this to some extent
really clarifies what Heron
of Alexandria was up to.
I suppose we stop now, are there
any questions?
- So when you define
AVERAGE-DAMP, don't you need
to have a variable, f?
- Ah, the question was, and here
we're having again:
You gotta learn about the syntax.
The question was, when defining
AVERAGE-DAMP, don't you have
to have a variable, defined with f?
What you're asking is the formal
parameter of f?
- Yeah.
- Okay, the formal parameter
of f is here.
The formal parameter of f ...
- The formal parameter of
AVERAGE-DAMP.
- f is being applied to
an argument, right?
Then it's indeed true that f must
have a formal parameter.
Let's find out what f's
formal parameter is.
- The formal parameter of
AVERAGE-DAMP.
- Oh, f is the formal parameter
of AVERAGE-DAMP.
I'm sorry, you're just confusing
a syntactic thing.
I could have written this
the other way.
I'm sorry I didn't understand
your question.
Of course I could have written it
this other way.
Those are identical notations.
This is a different way of writing
this:
You're gonna have to
get used to lambda notation,
'cause I'm gonna use it.
Okay,
what it says here, I'm defining
the name AVERAGE-DAMP
to name the procedure
who is of one argument f.
That's the formal parameter
of the procedure AVERAGE-DAMP.
What this define does,
is it says,
give this name a value.
Here is the value for it.
There happens to be a
funny syntax to make that easier
in some cases,
it's purely convenience.
But the reason why I wrote it
this way here is to emphasize,
that I'm dealing with a
procedure, that takes a
procedure as its argument, and
produces a procedure as its value.
- I don't understand why
you use lambda trice.
Can you just use one lambda
and take two arguments f and x?
- No.
- No?
- That would be a different thing.
If I were to write the procedure
lambda of f and x, the
average of x and x,
That would not be something,
which would be allowed to take
a procedure as an argument, and
produce a procedure as its value.
That would be a thing that takes
a procedure as its argument, and
a number as its argument, and
produces a new number.
But what I'm producing here is a
procedure to fit in the procedure
slot over here, which is going
to be used over here.
So the number has to come
from here.
This is the thing that's gonna
eventually end up in the x.
And if you're confused you should
do some substitution, and
see for yourself.
Yes?
- Would you please show the
definition for AVERAGE-DAMP
without using lambda notation?
- Oh, I can't make a very simple
one like that. Let me do it for you
though, okay?
I can get rid of this lambda easily.
I don't wanna be... okay.
Actually I'm lying to you.
I don't wanna do what you want.
'cause I think it's more confusing
than you think.
I'm not
gonna write what you want.
We have to give it a name...
FOO, of X, to be...
... of F, of X, and X, ...
... and return as a value FOO.
This is equivalent.
But I have to
make an arbitrary name up.
This is equivalent to this
without any lambdas.
Okay? Since lambda is very
convenient for naming
anonymous procedures. It's the
anonymous name of something.
Now, if you really wanna know
a cute way of doing this,
we'll talk about it later.
Where you don't have to define
the anonymous procedure.
Okay, other questions?
I suppose we go
for our break again.
So now we've seen how to
use higher-order procedures,
they're called. That's procedures
that take procedural arguments
and produce procedural values,
to help us clarify and abstract
some otherwise
complicated processes.
I suppose what I'd like to do now
is have a bit of fun with that,
and sort of
a little practice as well.
So let's play with this
square root thing even more,
let's elaborate it and understand
what's going on and make use of
this kind of programming style.
But one thing that you might
know is that there's a
general method called Newton's
method, the purpose of which
is to find the roots - that's the
zeroes - of functions.
So, for example, to find a y,
such that
f of y equals zero.
We start with some guess,
this is Newton's method.
And the guess we'll start with,
we'll call y_0.
And then we will iterate the
following expression:
y_(n+1)
- this is a difference equation -
is y_n minus f of y_n over the
derivative with respect to y, of f,
evaluated at y equal y_n.
Very strange notation.
I must say, ugh.
The derivative of f
with respect to y
is a function.
And I'm having a little bit
of unhappiness with that, but
that's all right.
Turns out the programming
language world notation
is much clearer.
Now what is this?
This is what's called
Newton's method.
It's a method for finding
the roots of the function f.
And it of course, sometimes
converges, and it does so
very fast,
and sometimes it doesn't
converge, and... oh well, we'll
have to do something else.
But let's talk about sqaure root
by Newton's method.
Well that's rather interesting.
Let's do exactly the same
thing we did last time.
A bit of wishful thinking.
We will apply Newton's method,
assuming we knew how to do it.
We don't know how to do it yet.
Well, let's go.
What do I have here?
the square root of x.
It's Newton's method, applied to
a procedure which will represent
that function of y, which
computes that function of y.
Well that procedure is that
procedure of y, which is the
difference between x and the
square of y.
Indeed, if I had a value of y,
for which this were 0, then y
would be the square root of x.
See that?
Okay, I'm gonna start this out,
searching at 1, again, completely
arbitrary property of square roots
that I can do that.
Now, how am I gonna compute
Newton's method?
Well, Newton's method, I have it
right here.
In fact, what I'm doing is
looking for a fixed point
of some procedure.
This procedure involves some
complicated expressions in terms
of other complicated things.
But I'm trying to find the
fixed point of this.
I wanna find the values of y,
which if I put y in here,
I get the same value out here.
Up to some degree of accuracy.
Well I already have a fixed-point
process around to do that.
So let's just define Newton's
method over here.
A procedure which computes a function, and a guess, initial guess.
Now, I'm going to have to
do something here.
I'm going to need a
derivative of the function...
I'm gonna need a procedure
which computes the derivative
of the function, computed by the
given procedure f.
I'm trying to be very carful about
what I say.
I don't wanna mix up
the word procedure and function,...
function's a mathematical word,
it says a mapping from values to
other values, set of ordered pairs,
okay.
But I sometimes
accidentially mix those up.
Procedures compute functions.
So I'm gonna define the
derivative of f to be, by wishful
thinking again, I don't know how
I'm gonna do it.
Let's worry about that later.
... of F.
So if F is a procedure, which
happens to be this one over
here for a square root,
then DF will be the derivative
of it. which is it also...
Well, the derivative of the
function computed by
that procedure.
DF will be a
procedure that computes the
derivative of the function,
computed by the procedure F.
And then, given that, I will just
go looking for a fixed point.
What is the fixed point I'm
looking for?
It's the one for that procedure
of one argument x, which I
compute by subtracting x of the
old... the y_n here.
The quotient of f of x, and df of x.
Starting out with the
original guess.
That's all very simple.
Now I have one part left that
I haven't written.
And I want you to see the process
by which I write these things,
'cause this is really true.
I start out with some
mathematical idea, perhaps.
By wishful thinking I assume that,
by some magic, I can do
something that I have a name for.
I'm not gonna worry about how
I do it yet.
Now I go walking down here and
say, well, by some magic, I'm
somehow gonna figure how to
do that.
But I'm gonna write my
program anyway.
Wishful thinking - essential to
good engineering.
And certainly essential to good
computer science.
Okay, so anyway..
How many of you wish that
your computer ran faster?
Well, the derivative isn't so
bad either, sort of like
average-damping.
Derivative is a procedure that
takes a procedure that computes
a function as its argument.
And it produces a procedure
that computes a function
which needs one argument x.
Well, we all know this defintion.
It's f of x plus delta x minus
f of x over delta x, right?
For some small delta x.
So that's the quotient of the
difference of f of the sum of
x and dx, ...
... minus f point x, divided by dx.
I think the thing was lining up
correctly, when I balanced
the parentheses.
Now I want you to look at this.
Just look.
I suppose I haven't told you what
dx is, somewhere in the world I'm
gonna have to write it down.
Well something like that.
I'm not interested.
This is a procedure which takes
a procedure and produces an
approximation.. , a procedure that
computes an approximation of the
derivative of the function
computed by the procedure given.
By the standard methods that
you all know and love.
Now, it may not be the case that
doing this operation is such a
good way of approximating
a derivative.
The numerical analysists here
should jump on me and say:
"Don't do that!"
"Computing derivatives produces
noisy answers!", which is true.
However this again is for the
sake of understanding.
Look at what we've got.
We've started out with what
is apparently a mathematically
complex thing.
And in a few blackboards full,
we've managed to decompose
the problem of computing square
roots by the way you were
taught in your college
calculus class, Newton's method.
So that it can be understood.
It's clear.
Let's look at the structure of
what it is we've got.
Let's look at this slide.
This is a diagram of the machine
described by the program on the
blackboard.
There's a machine described here.
And what have I got?
Over here is the Newton's
method, Newton's method
function f, that we have on
the left-most blackboard.
It's a thing which takes an
argument called y and puts out
the difference between x and
the square of y.
Where x is some sort of free
variable that comes in from
the outside, ...
... by some magic.
So the square root routine
picks up an x, ...
... picks up an x, and builds this
procedure, which has the x rolled
up in it, by substitution.
Now, this procedure in the
cloud is fed in as the f, okay.
Into the Newton's method,
which is here, this box.
The f is fanned out, part of it
goes into something else, and
the other part of it goes into
a derivative process into
something else, ...
... to produce a procedure, which
computes the function, which is
the iteration function of
Newton's method when we use a
fixed-point method.
So this, this procedure, which
contains in it, by substitution...
Remember, Newton's method
over here, Newton's method
builds this procedure,
And Newton's method has in it
defined f and df.
So those are captured over here,
f and df.
Starting with this procedure, I
can now feed this to the fixed
point process, with an initial
guess coming out from the
outside from square root,
to produce the square root of x.
So what we've built is a very
powerful engine, which allows
us to make nice things like this.
Now I want to end this with
basically an idea of Chris
Strachey, one of the grandfathers
of computer science.
He's a logician, who lived in the...
I suppose about 10 years ago or
15 years ago he died...
I don't remember exactly when.
He's one of the inventors of
something called
denontational semantics.
He was a great advocate of
making procedures, or functions,
first-class citizens
in a programming language.
So here's the rights and privileges
of first-class citizens in a
programming language.
It allows you to make any
abstraction you like, if you
have functions as
first-class citizens.
They must be, the first-class
citizens must be able to be
named by variables.
And you're seeing me doing that
all the time.
Here is a nice variable which
names a procedure which
computes something.
There is a... they have to be
passed as arguments to
procedures.
Well, you've certainly seen that.
We have to be able to return
them, as values from procedures.
And I suppose we've seen that.
We haven't yet seen anything
about data structures.
We will soon.
But it's also the case, that in
order to have a first-class citizen
in a programming language, the
object has to be allowed to be
part of a data structure.
We're gonna see that soon.
So I just wanna close with this,
and say, this, having things like
procedures as first-class data
structures, first-class data
allows one to make powerful
abstractions.
Which encode general methods,
like Newton's method in a very
clear way.
Are there any questions?
Yes?
- Could you put DERIV instead of
DF directly in FIXED-POINT.
- Oh sure.
Yes, I could have put DERIV of F
right here, no question. Mhm.
Anytime you see something
defined you can put the
thing, that the defintion is, there.
And you should get
the same result.
In fact, what that would look
like, it's interesting ...
- Lambda, you could put the
lambda expression in there.
- I could also put the,
I could also put DERIV of F here.
It would look interesting.
Because we open-paren,
open-paren deriv of f
close-paren on x.
now that would have the bad property of computing the derivative many times.
'cause every time I would run
this procedure I would compute
the derivative again.
- (Right.)
- However, the two open-parens
here, both would be meaningful.
I want you to understand that
syntactically, that thats's a
sensible thing.
Whereas if were to rewrite this
program, and I should do it right
here, just so you see.
'cause that's a good question.
... of F and GUESS, to be
FIXED-POINT of that
procedure of one argument X,
which subtracts from X ...
... the quotient of F applied to X
and the DERIV of F applied to X.
Ahm, ... GUESS. Okay?
This is a
perfect little legitimate program,
because what I have here,
remember the evaluation rule.
The evaluation rule is:
Evaluate all of the parts of the
combination, the operator,
and the operands.
This is the operator of
this combination.
Evaluating
this operator will of course
produce the derivative of F.
- .. one step further you could put
the lambda expression in that ...
- Oh of course. Anytime I take
something which is defined, I
could put the thing it's defined
to be, in the place where
the thing defined is.
I can't remember which is
definiens and definiendum, ah,
when I'm trying to figure out
how to give a lecture about this in
freshman class I use such words,
and tell everybody it's fun to tell
their friends.
Okay, I think that's it.
GNU Free Documentation License
Version 1.3, 3 November 2008
Copyright  2000, 2001, 2002, 2007, 2008 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of this license document, but changing it is not allowed.
0. PREAMBLE
The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or other functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom: to assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it, with or without modifying it, either commercially or noncommercially. Secondarily, this License preserves for the author and publisher a way to get credit for their work, while not being considered responsible for modifications made by others.
This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that derivative works of the document must themselves be free in the same sense. It complements the GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft license designed for free software.
We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for free software, because free software needs free documentation: a free program should come with manuals providing the same freedoms that the software does. But this License is not limited to software manuals; it can be used for any textual work, regardless of subject matter or whether it is published as a printed book. We recommend this License principally for works whose purpose is instruction or reference.
1. APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS
This License applies to any manual or other work, in any medium, that contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be distributed under the terms of this License. Such a notice grants a world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use that work under the conditions stated herein. The "Document", below, refers to any such manual or work. Any member of the public is a licensee, and is addressed as "you". You accept the license if you copy, modify or distribute the work in a way requiring permission under copyright law.
A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work containing the Document or a portion of it, either copied verbatim, or with modifications and/or translated into another language.
A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter section of the Document that deals exclusively with the relationship of the publishers or authors of the Document to the Document's overall subject (or to related matters) and contains nothing that could fall directly within that overall subject. (Thus, if the Document is in part a textbook of mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any mathematics.) The relationship could be a matter of historical connection with the subject or with related matters, or of legal, commercial, philosophical, ethical or political position regarding them.
The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections whose titles are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the notice that says that the Document is released under this License. If a section does not fit the above definition of Secondary then it is not allowed to be designated as Invariant. The Document may contain zero Invariant Sections. If the Document does not identify any Invariant Sections then there are none.
The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that are listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that says that the Document is released under this License. A Front-Cover Text may be at most 5 words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25 words.
A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a machine-readable copy, represented in a format whose specification is available to the general public, that is suitable for revising the document straightforwardly with generic text editors or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint programs or (for drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that is suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic translation to a variety of formats suitable for input to text formatters. A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file format whose markup, or absence of markup, has been arranged to thwart or discourage subsequent modification by readers is not Transparent. An image format is not Transparent if used for any substantial amount of text. A copy that is not "Transparent" is called "Opaque".
Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML or XML using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple HTML, PostScript or PDF designed for human modification. Examples of transparent image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG. Opaque formats include proprietary formats that can be read and edited only by proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally available, and the machine-generated HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by some word processors for output purposes only.
The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page itself, plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly, the material this License requires to appear in the title page. For works in formats which do not have any title page as such, "Title Page" means the text near the most prominent appearance of the work's title, preceding the beginning of the body of the text.
The "publisher" means any person or entity that distributes copies of the Document to the public.
A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named subunit of the Document whose title either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in parentheses following text that translates XYZ in another language. (Here XYZ stands for a specific section name mentioned below, such as "Acknowledgements", "Dedications", "Endorsements", or "History".) To "Preserve the Title" of such a section when you modify the Document means that it remains a section "Entitled XYZ" according to this definition.
The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice which states that this License applies to the Document. These Warranty Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in this License, but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other implication that these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has no effect on the meaning of this License.
2. VERBATIM COPYING
You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the copyright notices, and the license notice saying this License applies to the Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no other conditions whatsoever to those of this License. You may not use technical measures to obstruct or control the reading or further copying of the copies you make or distribute. However, you may accept compensation in exchange for copies. If you distribute a large enough number of copies you must also follow the conditions in section 3.
You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above, and you may publicly display copies.
3. COPYING IN QUANTITY
If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly have printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the Document's license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back cover. Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify you as the publisher of these copies. The front cover must present the full title with all words of the title equally prominent and visible. You may add other material on the covers in addition. Copying with changes limited to the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the Document and satisfy these conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in other respects.
If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent pages.
If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document numbering more than 100, you must either include a machine-readable Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each Opaque copy a computer-network location from which the general network-using public has access to download using public-standard network protocols a complete Transparent copy of the Document, free of added material. If you use the latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps, when you begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure that this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the stated location until at least one year after the last time you distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or retailers) of that edition to the public.
It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors of the Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to give them a chance to provide you with an updated version of the Document.
4. MODIFICATIONS
You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document under the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you release the Modified Version under precisely this License, with the Modified Version filling the role of the Document, thus licensing distribution and modification of the Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it. In addition, you must do these things in the Modified Version:
* A. Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct from that of the Document, and from those of previous versions (which should, if there were any, be listed in the History section of the Document). You may use the same title as a previous version if the original publisher of that version gives permission.
* B. List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or entities responsible for authorship of the modifications in the Modified Version, together with at least five of the principal authors of the Document (all of its principal authors, if it has fewer than five), unless they release you from this requirement.
* C. State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the Modified Version, as the publisher.
* D. Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document.
* E. Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications adjacent to the other copyright notices.
* F. Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license notice giving the public permission to use the Modified Version under the terms of this License, in the form shown in the Addendum below.
* G. Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant Sections and required Cover Texts given in the Document's license notice.
* H. Include an unaltered copy of this License.
* I. Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its Title, and add to it an item stating at least the title, year, new authors, and publisher of the Modified Version as given on the Title Page. If there is no section Entitled "History" in the Document, create one stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as given on its Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified Version as stated in the previous sentence.
* J. Preserve the network location, if any, given in the Document for public access to a Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise the network locations given in the Document for previous versions it was based on. These may be placed in the "History" section. You may omit a network location for a work that was published at least four years before the Document itself, or if the original publisher of the version it refers to gives permission.
* K. For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications", Preserve the Title of the section, and preserve in the section all the substance and tone of each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or dedications given therein.
* L. Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document, unaltered in their text and in their titles. Section numbers or the equivalent are not considered part of the section titles.
* M. Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements". Such a section may not be included in the Modified Version.
* N. Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with any Invariant Section.
* O. Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.
If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material copied from the Document, you may at your option designate some or all of these sections as invariant. To do this, add their titles to the list of Invariant Sections in the Modified Version's license notice. These titles must be distinct from any other section titles.
You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various partiesfor example, statements of peer review or that the text has been approved by an organization as the authoritative definition of a standard.
You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text, and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version. Only one passage of Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through arrangements made by) any one entity. If the Document already includes a cover text for the same cover, previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same entity you are acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may replace the old one, on explicit permission from the previous publisher that added the old one.
The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this License give permission to use their names for publicity for or to assert or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.
5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS
You may combine the Document with other documents released under this License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for modified versions, provided that you include in the combination all of the Invariant Sections of all of the original documents, unmodified, and list them all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in its license notice, and that you preserve all their Warranty Disclaimers.
The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single copy. If there are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but different contents, make the title of each such section unique by adding at the end of it, in parentheses, the name of the original author or publisher of that section if known, or else a unique number. Make the same adjustment to the section titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of the combined work.
In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled "History" in the various original documents, forming one section Entitled "History"; likewise combine any sections Entitled "Acknowledgements", and any sections Entitled "Dedications". You must delete all sections Entitled "Endorsements".
6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS
You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other documents released under this License, and replace the individual copies of this License in the various documents with a single copy that is included in the collection, provided that you follow the rules of this License for verbatim copying of each of the documents in all other respects.
You may extract a single document from such a collection, and distribute it individually under this License, provided you insert a copy of this License into the extracted document, and follow this License in all other respects regarding verbatim copying of that document.
7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS
A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a storage or distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the copyright resulting from the compilation is not used to limit the legal rights of the compilation's users beyond what the individual works permit. When the Document is included in an aggregate, this License does not apply to the other works in the aggregate which are not themselves derivative works of the Document.
If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be placed on covers that bracket the Document within the aggregate, or the electronic equivalent of covers if the Document is in electronic form. Otherwise they must appear on printed covers that bracket the whole aggregate.
8. TRANSLATION
Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section 4. Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special permission from their copyright holders, but you may include translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition to the original versions of these Invariant Sections. You may include a translation of this License, and all the license notices in the Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers, provided that you also include the original English version of this License and the original versions of those notices and disclaimers. In case of a disagreement between the translation and the original version of this License or a notice or disclaimer, the original version will prevail.
If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements", "Dedications", or "History", the requirement (section 4) to Preserve its Title (section 1) will typically require changing the actual title.
9. TERMINATION
You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document except as expressly provided under this License. Any attempt otherwise to copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute it is void, and will automatically terminate your rights under this License.
However, if you cease all violation of this License, then your license from a particular copyright holder is reinstated (a) provisionally, unless and until the copyright holder explicitly and finally terminates your license, and (b) permanently, if the copyright holder fails to notify you of the violation by some reasonable means prior to 60 days after the cessation.
Moreover, your license from a particular copyright holder is reinstated permanently if the copyright holder notifies you of the violation by some reasonable means, this is the first time you have received notice of violation of this License (for any work) from that copyright holder, and you cure the violation prior to 30 days after your receipt of the notice.
Termination of your rights under this section does not terminate the licenses of parties who have received copies or rights from you under this License. If your rights have been terminated and not permanently reinstated, receipt of a copy of some or all of the same material does not give you any rights to use it.
10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE
The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in detail to address new problems or concerns. See http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/.
Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version number. If the Document specifies that a particular numbered version of this License "or any later version" applies to it, you have the option of following the terms and conditions either of that specified version or of any later version that has been published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation. If the Document does not specify a version number of this License, you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation. If the Document specifies that a proxy can decide which future versions of this License can be used, that proxy's public statement of acceptance of a version permanently authorizes you to choose that version for the Document.
11. RELICENSING
"Massive Multiauthor Collaboration Site" (or "MMC Site") means any World Wide Web server that publishes copyrightable works and also provides prominent facilities for anybody to edit those works. A public wiki that anybody can edit is an example of such a server. A "Massive Multiauthor Collaboration" (or "MMC") contained in the site means any set of copyrightable works thus published on the MMC site.
"CC-BY-SA" means the Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0 license published by Creative Commons Corporation, a not-for-profit corporation with a principal place of business in San Francisco, California, as well as future copyleft versions of that license published by that same organization.
"Incorporate" means to publish or republish a Document, in whole or in part, as part of another Document.
An MMC is "eligible for relicensing" if it is licensed under this License, and if all works that were first published under this License somewhere other than this MMC, and subsequently incorporated in whole or in part into the MMC, (1) had no cover texts or invariant sections, and (2) were thus incorporated prior to November 1, 2008.
The operator of an MMC Site may republish an MMC contained in the site under CC-BY-SA on the same site at any time before August 1, 2009, provided the MMC is eligible for relicensing.